A Guide to the Rockefeller Brothers Fund records, Projects (Grants), RG 3, Subgroup 1 and Subgroup 2 FA005
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Brothers Fund records, Projects (Grants), RG 3, Subgroup 1 and Subgroup 2
1947-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
FA005
750 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection has been donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by RBF.
File Plan
Former Classification: V
Biographical/Historical note
The Rockefeller Brothers Fund (RBF) was established in 1940 by the five sons of John D. Rockefeller Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller: John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David Rockefeller, as a vehicle for the members of the Brothers generation to systematically coordinate their philanthropic giving as well as share consultants, advice, and resources. Its endowment was created through a gift from JDR Jr. in 1951, and a subsequent bequest from his estate in 1960. Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, the eldest sibling and the only daughter of John D. Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, joined the RBF Board in 1954.
John D. Rockefeller 3rd served as president of the Fund from its inception until 1956. Other past presidents have included: Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1956-1958; Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1958-1968; Dana S. Creel, 1968-1975; William M. Dietel, 1975-1987; and Colin G. Campbell, 1998-2000.
Scope and Contents note
The project files include grant administration records, correspondence, reports, grant actions, grant products, and other associated material that document the philanthropic work of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Togo; Ghana; Public welfare; Religion; Education; Nigeria; New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy; Civic improvement; Race and society; Africa, West; International relations; Restoration and conservation; Population; Race relations
- Projects (Grants), 1947-1996; 3; 750 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Content Note
  Grant-making is the core of Rockefeller Brothers Fund operations. The RBF makes grants to local, national, and international philanthropic organizations that depend on the general public for funding. Principally, contributions are made to organizations whose activities reach a large number of people. The RBF's program has also included support for, and in some instances direct operation of, experimental or new undertakings.
  RG 3 Project/Grant Files includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial records, and background material relating to grant applications and grant administration.
  Each file contains records documenting the grant-giving history of the RBF with that given institution. They are not arranged by grant number. The files are presented alphabetically by the institutional name of the grant recipient, and further arranged by date. A specific institution may have received more than one grant for any given time period represented in the folder. Dates are inclusive, and reflect the dates of material within the folders; they can not be taken to represent continuous support, although in some cases continuous support may indeed have been given.
  The distinction between Subgroup 1 and Subgroup 2 is artificial, primarily dependent on the date that the material was shipped to RAC.
  Record Group 3.1, Box 1-1123 (561.5 cu. ft.), consists of material dated 1941-1989 and received by RAC through 1990.
  Record Group 3.2, Box 1124-1492 (184.5 cu. ft.), consists of material dated 1967-2003 (bulk: 1980-1995) and received by RAC after 1990.
  Documentation of the grant activity of a given institution may appear in both Subgroups.
  Subjects include civic improvement, cultural advancement, education, health, religion, welfare, international relations and understanding, conservation, population, and racial equality in the United States and abroad.
  Arrangement
  The Project/Grant files are arranged into two subgroups. Each subgroup is arranged alphabetically by institutional name of the grant recipient.
  Separated Materials note
  Books and publications which were originally contained in the grant files have been systematically separated to the RAC Library. Photographs and special format materials have been separated from their original location within specific grant files to best meet their preservation and conservation needs. Please refer to the inventory, and to the individual separation notes found in the files themselves, for applicable details.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material ten years old or older is open for scholarly research
  - Projects (Grants), 1947-1989; 1
    Scope and Contents
    Series 3 includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial records, and background material relating to grant applications and grant administration. Subjects include civic improvement, cultural advancement, education, health, religion, welfare, international relations and understanding, conservation, population, and racial equality in the U.S. and abroad.
    - A Better Chance, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Related Materials
      Formerly: Independent Schools Talent Search.
    - A Better Chance, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A Better Chance, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - A Better Chance, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A Better Chance, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A Better Chance, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - A Better Chance, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - A Better Chance, Financial Information, 1965-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - A Better Chance, Publications, Annual Reports, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - A Better Chance, Publications, Annual Reports, 1970-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - A Better Chance, Publications, Annual Development Reports, Newsletter, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - A Bunch of Experimental Theaters of New York, Inc., 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, Inc., 1967-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13A)
    - A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, Inc., 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13B)
    - A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, Inc., Tax Information (Box 2A, Folder 13C)
    - Abbott House, 1963-1964 (Box 2A, Folder 14A)
    - Abbott House, 1965-1968 (Box 2A, Folder 14B)
    - Abbott House, 1969-1970 (Box 2A, Folder 15)
    - Abbott House, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Abbott House, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Abbott House, Financial Information, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., 1965-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Financial Information, 1970-1982 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Publications, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Publications, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Publications, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Publications, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Publications, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Academy of Political Science, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Academy of Political Science, Publications, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Acción Comunitaria del Perú, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Separated Materials
      17 photographs with text (19 pages total) relocated to Rockefeller Brothers Fund photographs box 1493
    - Acción Comunitaria del Perú, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Acción Comunitaria del Perú, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Acción Comunitaria del Perú, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Acción Comunitaria del Perú, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Acción Comunitaria del Perú, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Acción International, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Acción International, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Acción International, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Acción International, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Acción International, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Acción International, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      22 photographs with text (12 pages total) relocated to Rockefeller Brothers Fund photographs box 1493
    - Acción International, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Acción International, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Acción International, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Acción International, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Acción International, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Acción International, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Acción International, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Acción International, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Acción International, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Acción International, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Acción International, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Acción International, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Acción International, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Acción International, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Acción International, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Acción International, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Acción International, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities (formerly: American Council to Improve our Neighborhoods), 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - ACTION - Council for Better Cities, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - Adlai Stevenson Institute of International Affairs, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Adlai Stevenson Institute of International Affairs, 1967-1969 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Adlai Stevenson Institute of International Affairs, 1970-1972 (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - Adlai Stevenson Institute of International Affairs, 1972-1974 (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Administration and Management Research Association of New York City, Inc., 1971-1975 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Adoption Service of Westchester, Inc. (formerly: Adoption Service Fund of Westchester, Inc.), 1953 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - Adoption Service of Westchester, Inc., 1954 (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Adoption Service of Westchester, Inc., 1955-1957 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    - Adoption Service of Westchester, Inc., 1958-1960 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - Advisory for Open Education, 1971-1974 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1974 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1974 (Box 11, Folder 79)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1974-1975 (Box 11, Folder 80)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1975 (Box 11, Folder 81)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1975 (Box 11, Folder 82)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1976 (Box 11, Folder 83)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1976 (Box 11, Folder 84)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1976 (Box 11, Folder 85)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1976 (Box 11, Folder 86)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1977 (Box 12, Folder 87)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1977 (Box 12, Folder 88)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1977 (Box 12, Folder 89)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 90)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 91)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 92)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1978 (Box 13, Folder 93)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1979 (Box 13, Folder 94)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 95)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1980 (Box 13, Folder 96)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1980 (Box 13, Folder 97)
    - Advisory Services for Better Housing, Inc., 1981 (Box 13, Folder 98)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc. (formerly: Alternative Solutions for Exceptional Children, Inc.), 1973-1975 (Box 13, Folder 99)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 100)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 1979 (Box 14, Folder 101)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 1980 (Box 14, Folder 102)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 103)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 1983-1985 (Box 14, Folder 104)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., Education in the Eighties, 1979-1982 (Box 14, Folder 105)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., Education in the Eighties, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 106)
    - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., Education in the Eighties, 1982-1983 (Box 14, Folder 107)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 108)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1967 (Box 14, Folder 109)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 110)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1969 (Box 15, Folder 111)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1970 (Box 15, Folder 112)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1970 (Box 15, Folder 113)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1970 (Box 15, Folder 114)
    - Africa, Background Papers (J. Hyde and R. Scrivner Memos and Correspondence), 1970 (Box 15, Folder 115)
    - Africa, Background Papers (James Hyde and William Moody), 1971 (Box 15, Folder 116)
    - Africa, Background Papers (James Hyde and William Moody), 1972 (Box 15, Folder 117)
    - Africa News Service, Inc., 1978 (Box 15, Folder 118)
    - Africa News Service, Inc., 1979 (Box 16, Folder 119)
    - Africa News Service, Inc., 1980 (Box 16, Folder 120)
    - Africa News Service, Inc., 1981 (Box 16, Folder 121)
    - Africa News Service, Inc., 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 122)
    - Africa News Service, Inc., 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 123)
    - Africa Service Institute of New York, Inc., 1960-1962 (Box 16, Folder 124)
    - Africa Service Institute of New York, Inc., 1963 (Box 16, Folder 125)
    - Africa Service Institute of New York, Inc., 1964 (Box 16, Folder 126)
    - Africa Service Institute of New York, Inc., 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 127)
    - African Affairs Society of America, Ltd. (formerly: Pan-Africa Society of America, Ltd.), 1957-1961 (Box 17, Folder 128)
    - African Affairs Society of America, Ltd., 1962-1967 (Box 17, Folder 129)
    - African-American Institute (formerly: Institute of African-American Relations), Correspondence, 1953-1962 (Box 17, Folder 130)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 131)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 17, Folder 132)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 133)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 134)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 135)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 136)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 137)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 138)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 139)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 140)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 141)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 142)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 143)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 144)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 145)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 146)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1977 (Box 19, Folder 147)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 148)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 149)
    - African-American Institute, Correspondence, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 150)
    - African-American Institute, Financial Information, 1960-1964 (Box 19, Folder 151)
    - African-American Institute, Financial Information, 1966-1968 (Box 19, Folder 152)
    - African-American Institute, Financial Information, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 153)
    - African-American Institute, Financial Information, 1971-1972 (Box 20, Folder 154)
    - African-American Institute, Financial Information, 1973-1975 (Box 20, Folder 155)
    - African-American Institute, Financial Information, 1976-1978 (Box 20, Folder 156)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Annual Reports, 1959-1974 (Box 20, Folder 157)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Annual Reports, 1975-1978 (Box 20, Folder 158)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Conferences, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 159)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Conferences, 1971-1975 (Box 20, Folder 160)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Conferences, 1976-1979 (Box 21, Folder 161)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Quarterly Reports, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 162)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Quarterly Reports, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 163)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Quarterly Reports, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 164)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Quarterly Reports, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 165)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Quarterly Reports, 1968-1970 (Box 21, Folder 166)
    - African-American Institute, Publication, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1955-1964 (Box 21, Folder 167)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 168)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1971 (Box 22, Folder 169)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 170)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 171)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 172)
    - African-American Institute, Publications, Supplemental Reports and Publications, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 173)
    - African-American Institute, African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU), 1963 (Box 22, Folder 174)
    - African-American Institute, African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU), 1964 (Box 22, Folder 175)
    - African-American Institute, African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU), 1965 (Box 22, Folder 176)
    - African-American Institute, African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 177)
    - African-American Institute, African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU), 1966 (Box 23, Folder 178)
    - African-American Institute, African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU), 1966-1967 (Box 23, Folder 179)
    - African-American Institute, ASPAU Forum, 1963-1964 (Box 23, Folder 180)
    - African-American Institute, ASPAU Forum, 1965-1967 (Box 23, Folder 181)
    - African-American Institute, American Committee for Assistance to Tunisia, 1969-1973 (Box 23, Folder 182)
    - African-American Institute, Background Readings on United States Corporations in Southern Africa (vol. 1), June 1971 (Box 23, Folder 183)
    - African-American Institute, Background Readings on United States Corporations in Southern Africa (vol. 2), October 1971 (Box 24, Folder 184)
    - African-American Institute, Background Readings on United States Corporations in Southern Africa (vol. 2), October 1971 (Box 24, Folder 185)
    - African-American Institute, Background Readings on United States Corporations in Southern Africa (vol. 2), October 1971 (Box 24, Folder 186)
    - African-American Institute, Botswana National Commission on Education, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 187)
    - African-American Institute, Botswana National Commission on Education, 1975-1976 (Box 24, Folder 188)
    - African-American Institute, Botswana National Commission on Education, 1977-1979 (Box 24, Folder 189)
    - African-American Institute, Dana S. Creel AAI Travel Award, 1979 (Box 24, Folder 190)
    - African-American Institute, European Center for Overseas Industrial Equipment and Development (CEDIMOM), 1968-1969 (Box 25, Folder 191)
    - African-American Institute, European Center for Overseas Industrial Equipment and Development (CEDIMOM), 1969 (Box 25, Folder 192)
    - African-American Institute, European Center for Overseas Industrial Equipment and Development (CEDIMOM), 1970 (Box 25, Folder 193)
    - African-American Institute, European Center for Overseas Industrial Equipment and Development (CEDIMOM), 1971 (Box 25, Folder 194)
    - African-American Institute, Griswold Trip, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 195)
    - African-American Institute, Griswold Trip, 1965-1966 (Box 25, Folder 196)
    - African-American Institute, Institutional Investors Survey, 1971-1972 (Box 26, Folder 197)
    - African-American Institute, Institutional Investors Survey, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 198)
    - African-American Institute, Institutional Investors Survey, 1972-1974 (Box 26, Folder 199)
    - African-American Institute, School Leaver Project, 1969-1970 (Box 26, Folder 200)
    - African-American Institute, School Leaver Project, 1970-1971 (Box 26, Folder 201)
    - African-American Institute, School Services Division, 1972-1977 (Box 26, Folder 202)
    - African-American Institute, Women's Africa Committee, Ethiopian Women's Welfare Association (EWWA), 1959-1968 (Box 26, Folder 203)
    - African-American Institute, Women's Africa Committee, Ethiopian Women's Welfare Association (EWWA), 1969 (Box 27, Folder 204)
    - African-American Institute, Women's Africa Committee, Ethiopian Women's Welfare Association (EWWA), 1970-1971 (Box 27, Folder 205)
    - African-American Institute, Women's Africa Committee, Ethiopian Women's Welfare Association (EWWA), 1972 (Box 27, Folder 206)
    - African-American Institute, Women's Africa Committee, Ethiopian Women's Welfare Association (EWWA), 1973-1977 (Box 27, Folder 207)
    - African Wildlife Husbandry Development Association, 1974 (Box 27, Folder 208)
    - African Wildlife Husbandry Development Association, 1975 (Box 27, Folder 209)
    - African Wildlife Husbandry Development Association, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 210)
    - African Wildlife Husbandry Development Association, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 211)
      2 slides relocated to Rockefeller Brothers Fund photographs box 1493
    - African Wildlife Husbandry Development Association, 1977 (Box 27, Folder 212)
      3 photographs relocated to Rockefeller Brothers Fund photographs box 1493